<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present correction and reproof of sin or A discourse on 2 Jer. 19. vers. Thine own iniquities shall correct thee, &amp; thy backslideings shall reprove thee.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221463</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2060:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present correction and reproof of sin or A discourse on 2 Jer. 19. vers. Thine own iniquities shall correct thee, &amp; thy backslideings shall reprove thee.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 10, p. 10, 10-48 p. ; 4to.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Eaglesfield, at the Marigold, near Sarisburry-court in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRESENT CORRECTION AND REPROOF of SIN, OR A Diſcourſe on 2 Jer. 19. vers. <hi>Thine own Iniquities shall correct thee, &amp; thy Backſlideings shall reprove thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Hoc ſunt peccata<hi> Lapſis, </hi>quod grando Frugibus, quod turbidum ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Arboribus, quod Armentis peſtilens vaſtitas, quod Navigiis ſaeva Tempeſtas. <bibl>Cyprian Serm. de Lapſis.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>J. Eaglesfield,</hi> at the Marigold, near Sarisburry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court in Fleetſtreet. 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37239:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37239:2"/>
            <head>TO His much Honoured Friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. * * *.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have not adventur'd to diſpleas you by publishing your Name to the World; wherby you will eaſily apprehend, that I ſend you this Diſcourſe as to a Friend, for your impartial Opinion of it; rather than to a Patron for Protection: (the ſtale Complement of Epiſtles Dedicatory.) I deſigned it should have been accompanied with ſeveral other Diſcourſes, concerning the <hi>Evill of Sin,</hi> and its Agravations. <hi>Firſt,</hi> in relation to the <hi>B. Trinity;</hi> as it dishonours God, dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth the Divine Nature, &amp; beſpatters every Attribute &amp; Perfection of the Godhead; &amp; conſequently ſtrikes at the very being of a <hi>God.</hi> As it is a Rebellion againſt his Souve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raingty; Enmity to his Holineſs; a Provocation to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; a Contempt of his Wisdom; an ungratefull Affront to his infinite Goodneſs; challenging his Allmighty Power; giveing the Lye to his invariable Truth; ſlighting his Omniſcience; wearying his Patience; &amp;c. as it oppoſeth his Glory, &amp; contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts
<pb facs="tcp:37239:3"/>his holy Will, &amp; the great deſign of all his Revelations, Inſtitutions, &amp; Providences. <hi>Secondly,</hi> with reſpect to us as it thwarts the end of our Creation, perverts our rational Faculties, and the very principles of our Nature: as it blurrs the Image of God upon our Souls; robs us of his Delight &amp; Love; &amp; renders us uncapable of any friendly Convers &amp; Communion with him. As it deforms &amp; defiles the Soul; inſlaves us to many foolish &amp; hurtfull Luſts; as it gratifyes the Devil, &amp; brings us under his power; as it infects others with its contagion; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbs Societies; is the great Make-bate of the world, and the fatal ſource of all he Miſchiefs and Calamities, under which the Creation groans, and <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In compariſon with all <hi>other Evills</hi> of Affliction and Punishment: wherby ſin will appear to be the moſt pernicious and intolerable Evill: eſpecially as the cauſe of the Eternal Ruine of Souls. Where I intended to conſider the certainty of that <hi>Everlaſting Deſtruction</hi> threatned in Holy Scripture to the finally Impenitent. A Doctrine which ſo many would feign perſuade themſelv's to doubt of. I cannot wonder at it, ſince Intreſt and Inclination are inſtead of Evidence in other caſes as well as this: men are loath to admit any ſuch Premiſes, whoſe Concluſion would ingage them to change their cours of Life: it is not therfore ſtrange if after haveing forfeited the Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heaven, they endeavor to extinguish the flames of Hell. But being at preſent diverted from finishing what I began in that kind, I am deſired to let this be publisht alone. I have not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke the Readers candor, as is uſual, by repreſenting in a Preface the ſeaſonableneſs &amp; uſefullneſs of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:37239:3"/>treated of; becauſe both are ſufficiently obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>There is hardly any man whoſe Experience &amp; obſervation will not oblige him to acknowledg, that Sin doth very often cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect &amp; reprove the ſinner in this world. The Evidence is too ſadly notorious to be denyed, in the miſerable Catastrophe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtats, in the afflictive conſequences of great Transgreſsions, &amp; in the ordinary fruits of Luſt &amp; Folly, Lewdneſs, &amp; Paſsion, Intemperance &amp; unrighteouſneſs, &amp; a disorderly Life. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, thro the deceitfullneſs of Sin, &amp; the ſubtility of the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the neglect of Conſideration, the powerfull Influence of bad Company, and ſometimes the Righteous Judgment of God, (ſuffering men to harden themſelv's in their wickedneſs) the far greater part will not receive Inſtruction by this voice of the Rod; but turn the deaf Ear to all the Calls of God; &amp; will not be reclaim'd, by all the methods of his Grace, to bring them to Repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> by the following acount that is given of it, you will be furnisht with abundant matter of Thanksgiving to God: who partly by the early communications of his Grace, and the pious Care of thoſe who had the conduct of your younger years; &amp; partly by the kindneſs of his Providence, in keeping you at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from Temptations; &amp; by your own vigilance &amp; prudent Caution in places &amp; ſeaſons of Danger; hath preſerved you from thoſe Vices, which are thus attended with Temporal ſufferings. Such an Improvement of this Diſcours should be made by all thoſe happy Perſons, who cannot confirm
<pb facs="tcp:37239:4"/>this ſad Truth by their own Experience, ſave in very few &amp; the leſs conſiderable Inſtances of it.</p>
            <p>The beſt men may reap this Benefit by peruſing it: that the conſideration of the mighty Prevalence &amp; Growth of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, with the preſent bitter fruits of it, may promote their being crucifyed to this World, and willingneſs to quit it, aſſoon as God shall pleaſe: &amp; ſo diſpoſe them to deſire &amp; wait to be tranſlated to a better ſtate; where they shall neither Sin, nor feel the ſmart of Sin any more for ever; or be greiv'd &amp; ſadned by the ſins or Sufferings of other men.</p>
            <p>In this Life our corrupted Nature is not perfectly healed, but doth ever &amp; anon caſt forth Mire &amp; Dirt. Tho we are dyeing dayly unto Sin, &amp; long for the funeral of the old man; t' is not quite Dead; neither will it intirely be ſo, till our own Diſſolution: on which acount the Deceitfullneſs &amp; deſperate Wickedneſs of the heart diſcovers it ſelf in an hour of Temptation. So that ſome of thoſe, who were thought to be Eſtablisht &amp; Confirmed Chriſtians, have dishonor'd the name of God by ſcandalous Backſlideings, diſcredited their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, falſifyed their moſt ſolemn vows and obligations, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the hearts of ſome, &amp; weakned the hands of others, and shamefully diſparaged the Religion of our B. Saviour. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon God teſtifves his displeaſure by inward and ſometimes outward Troubles: a terrifyed Conſcience writes bitter things againſt them; or God denies the aids of his Grace, after ſuch a forfeiture; and their minds are darkn'd, their hearts hardned by degrees, &amp; they become careleſs and remiſs in the
<pb facs="tcp:37239:4"/>Matters of Religion, &amp; continue in their ſecurity; till by a ſevere Providence, or a more than ordinary Grace, they are awaken'd to conſider their ways, and remember whence they have fallen, &amp; Repent; &amp; therby recover his loſt favor, &amp; God reſtores the Joy of his Salvation.</p>
            <p>But this, Sir, is our Encouragement, &amp; ought to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative to continued watchfullneſs, &amp; the utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to perſevere, that if we are faithfull to the Death, (which may be nearer then we are aware) we shall then enter into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God, &amp; <hi>Sin no more.</hi> We shall no more provoke him to Anger, by our Apoſtacy; or ſuffer his correcting Rebukes for our Backſlideings. We shall no more be expoſed to Temptation; or ſeduced by Satan, to defile our Conſciences, to deſtroy the Peace of our minds, &amp; greive the H. Spirit of God. We shall no more ſtart aſide like a broken Bow, &amp; violate our holy promiſes &amp; Reſolutions. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance shall no longer darken our minds, or unmortifyed Luſt lay lurking in the Heart, or the Body any more betray the ſoul by unruly paſsions to the Commiſsion of Folly. And as the bleſſed Conſequent of a ſinleſs ſtate, no ſorrow shall ever more be felt, and therfore no complaint ever more he heard. Oh that thes thoughts were more delightfull &amp; more connatural to us! This should be the higheſt of our Wishes, and the object of our moſt deliberate &amp; Reſolved Choice; to be made more pertakers of the Divine Life; &amp; to glorifye God by a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect conformity to his holy Image. I moſt heartily be ſeech the great Sanctifyer &amp; Lover of ſouls to effect it more &amp; more on
<pb facs="tcp:37239:5"/>the my own heart &amp; yours. And tho one Kingdom do not hold us, &amp; I may never ſee your Face on Earth againe; yet before that glorious Everlaſting Kingdom we expect, (when by ſeeing God, we shall be changed into his likeneſs,) we may dayly meet at the Throne of Grace; &amp; there I humbly beg you would be my Remembrancer, as I promiſe to be yours. I moſt affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kiſſe your hands, &amp; remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Humble Servant JOHN. SHOWER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37239:5"/>
            <head>THE PRESENT CORRECTION AND REPROOF of SIN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>From 2 JER. 19. former part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For thine own wickedneſs ſhall correct thee, &amp; thy Backſlidings ſhall reprove thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words may be conſidered in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their cauſleſs revolt from the worſhip of the <hi>true God,</hi> and obedience to him. In the preceding verſes God acquits himſelf from the imputation of haveing ever given them or their Fathers any juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for ſuch an Apoſtacy.
<note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>What iniquity have your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers found in me, that they are gone far from me, and have walked after vanity and are become vaine.</hi> And then upbraids them with their ingratitude and folly, in the following verſes.
<note place="margin">V. 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Hath any nation changed their Gods which yet are no Gods? but my people have changed their glory for that which doth not profit. Be aſtoniſht, ô ye Heavens at this, and be horribly afraid, for my people have committed two evills, they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me the fountaine of liveing waters, and hewed them out
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37239:6"/>ciſterns, broken ciſterns that can hold no waters.</hi> Therupon God charges them as the authors of their own ruine, as haveing brought upon themſelfs the calamities under which they ſmarted.
<note place="margin">V. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>Is Iſrael a ſervant? is he an homeborn ſlave? why is he ſpoiled? Haſt thou not procured it unto thy ſelf, in that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God?</hi> In vaine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doſt thou ſeek for help to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or have recours unto the King of <hi>Aſſyria:</hi> for thou ſhalt eat of the fruit of thine own ways, <hi>Thine own wickedneſs ſhall correct thee, and thy Backſlidings ſhall reprove thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thine own <hi>wickedneſs</hi> ſhall <hi>correct</hi> thee,
<note place="margin">7 Hoſ. 15.</note> or thou ſhalt be bound and <hi>fetterr'd,</hi> and held in the chains of thine own ſins, as the original word doth ſometimes ſignifie. or rather, thou ſhalt beinſtructed and taught by thine own folly,
<note place="margin">4 Job. 3.</note> how <hi>evill</hi> and <hi>bitter a thing it is, to ſin againſt God.</hi> Which is the meaning of the word in other places, and therefore the <hi>Septuagint</hi> make uſe of a word in this place which ſignifies both, to <hi>teach</hi> and to <hi>chaſten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thy <hi>backſlidings</hi> ſhall <hi>reprove</hi> thee, or <hi>convince</hi> thee by argument and demonſtration. The <hi>fruit</hi> of thine <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy</hi> ſhall convince thee of the <hi>folly</hi> of it: in forſakeing the way of truth for lyeing vanities; the fountaine of living waters, for broken ciſterns. The miſerable effects &amp; conſequences of ſin ſhall <hi>correct</hi> and <hi>reprove</hi> thee.</p>
            <p>What is here ſpoken to a <hi>community,</hi> may be as truly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted of <hi>Individuals,</hi> and particular perſons, that the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities they ſuffer are the fruits of their own folly; that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37239:6"/>they bring miſeries on them ſelv's in this world; and are ten times ſeverely corrected and chaſtened by their own wickedneſs. My preſent deſign is, <hi>to make it evident that it is ſo,</hi> by ſhowing in ſeveral inſtances, <hi>how ſinners are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved &amp; punnisht by their own ſin and folly, even in this Life, as well as in the next.</hi> And then ſhall improve this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument by ſome <hi>practical inferences,</hi> which may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd from it. I ſhall endeavor to manifeſt this truth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which doth oftentimes <hi>proportion</hi> and <hi>ſuit</hi> temporal <hi>punishments</hi> to the <hi>ſins</hi> of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From <hi>the more immediate effects &amp; conſequences of Sin,</hi> which in this life do ordinarily correct and reprove the ſinner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may conſider, <hi>how the Juſtice of God doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentims ſuit the puniſhment to the ſin even in this Life.</hi> This is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, either on <hi>their own perſons</hi> who were guilty: or on <hi>their Relatives</hi> &amp; <hi>poſterity.</hi> As to the <hi>former,</hi> 2 ways. Either <hi>when one ſin is the punniſhment of another:</hi> or <hi>when ſome calamity is inflicted which is anſwerable</hi> to the ſin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God doth ſometimes correct ſinners in this world, <hi>in the puniſhment of one ſin by the permiſsion of more.</hi> Which may be either, by <hi>their own further ſin,</hi> or by <hi>the ſins of other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. God doth ſometimes punniſh former ſins, <hi>by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the offending perſon to commit more and greater.</hi> That this is the <hi>ſevereſt</hi> punishment of ſin in this life, may eaſily
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37239:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>be evinc'd. To be left of God to ſin on, &amp; to commit more &amp; greater abominations, is a kind of <hi>damnation,</hi> were there no other <hi>Hell</hi> to ſucceed it: for we know the the life of the <hi>Prodigal</hi> is dated from his <hi>Repentance,</hi> and not from his <hi>birth: This my ſon was dead, but is now alive.</hi> And that ſome of the heathens themſelv's have concluded any man to be more worthy of a publick lamentation, at the time of his <hi>debauchery,</hi> then of his <hi>death.</hi> Some ſins, 'tis true, have almoſt an inſeparable connection &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on each other, as luſt follows gluttony, and folly drunkenneſs: but God in righteous judgement may leave a man to the power of Temptation, &amp; ſuffer him to encreas the number, and add to the meaſure of his former ſins, &amp; ſo treaſure up wrath againſt the day of wrath. Thus he punniſht the <hi>wantoneſs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him to fall into <hi>Idolatry:</hi> and the <hi>covetousneſs</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das;</hi> by ſuffering him to <hi>betray</hi> his Lord, &amp; Peter's firſt <hi>denial</hi> of Chriſt, by his <hi>forſwearing</hi> him afterward. The <hi>Jews,</hi> for killing the <hi>Prophets,</hi> were left of God, to crucifye the <hi>Meſstah;</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they committed <hi>wheredoms</hi> with the Daughters of Moab,
<note place="margin">12 Numb. 1: 2.</note> were left to be inſnared by their <hi>Idolatry.</hi> One ſin makes way for more; as the Idolatry of the <hi>golden Calf</hi> was uſhered by intemperance &amp; Idleneſs:
<note place="margin">32 Ex.</note> 
               <hi>The people ſat down to eat, &amp; drink, and roſe up to play.</hi> Thus what men get by oppreſſion &amp; acts of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, they oftentimes ſpend in pride &amp; luxury. The wages of unrighteousneſs, or what they purchas'd by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37239:7"/>means, is ſinfully imploy'd &amp; waſted, and that ſo quickly ſometimes, as if they reſolved their <hi>ſilver and gold</hi> ſhould not tarry <hi>to witneſs againſt them.</hi> God ſuffers their <hi>treaſures of wickedneſs</hi> to melt away by intemperance &amp; riotous living. Beſides when one ſin is made a cloak to conceal another, and to hide the shame, or avoid the punniſhment of one crime, they are ſufferr'd to commit more: as <hi>Joſeph's Brethren,</hi> after their cruelty to him, in ſelling him into Aegypt, they were as unkind &amp; cruel to their aged <hi>Father</hi> in bringing him his bloudy coat, in revenge for his particular fondneſs &amp; affection to their <hi>Brother.</hi> After the commiſſion of any wickedneſs God may juſtly leave us to excuſe it with <hi>a Lye.</hi> Which is the greateſt folly imaginable, as therby profeſſing that it is better to be really guilty of <hi>two</hi> faults, then to be thought guilty of <hi>one.</hi> And then you may proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to protect that Lye by on oath, and at length grow impudent &amp; incorrigible. Therfore fear the beginnings of ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sometimes God corrects the ſins of one, by the ſins of another. Jacob</hi> the younger ſon ſtole his Father's bleſſing by the deceit of his elder Brothers garment: and not long after his Father in Law <hi>Laban,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 27.29.</note> by a like fraud gives him <hi>Leah</hi> inſtead of <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſubſtitutes the elder ſiſter in the room of the younger, whom he loved, and ſerved an apprenticeſhip for. God by the faults of other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men repays us for our own. As <hi>David's</hi> ſecret adultery,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37239:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>by <hi>Abſolon's</hi> openinceſt, in laying with his Father's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines: &amp; by the luſt of his ſon <hi>Ammon</hi> towards his ſiſter <hi>Tamar.</hi> And when <hi>David</hi> neglected to execute juſtice on <hi>Ammon</hi> for that offence, <hi>Abſolon</hi> injuſtly ſlew him. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid's</hi> treachery againſt <hi>Uriah</hi> was requited by the treaſon of his Son, and the rebellion of his own ſubjects, who joyn'd in conſpiracy with him againſt his Father. Thus God imployed the <hi>ambition</hi> of the King of <hi>Moab</hi> to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Jud. 9.14.</note> &amp; they became ſlaves for eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years to that people, with whoſe Idolatrous cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes they had wickedly complied. Thus thoſe who were <hi>disobedient</hi> to their <hi>Parents</hi> are oftentimes punniſht by the undutifullneſs of their own <hi>children. Unfaithfull</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants may meet with ſome hereafter who will be <hi>ſo</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God doth oftentimes in this world inflict ſome calamity that is ſuitable to the crime,</hi> and in ſome reſpect or other carries the reſemblance of it. And the Juſtice of God is more eſpecially viſible in the <hi>likeneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>proportion</hi> between the <hi>ſin</hi> and the <hi>punniſhment</hi> in theſe four reſpects. 1. In the <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>quality.</hi> 2. In the <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>meaſure.</hi> 3. As to the <hi>time.</hi> 4. As to the <hi>place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The kind and quality of the temporal punishment is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſuited to the kind and quality of the ſin.</hi> As men ſow, ſo they reap,
<note place="margin">8 Hoſ. 3.</note> and to every ſeed its own body. They <hi>plow wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſow iniquity,</hi> &amp; <hi>reap</hi> a punniſhment that is adapted to the ſin. <hi>They ſow the wind, and reap the whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37239:8"/>as the Prophet ſpeaks.
<note place="margin">14 Prov. 14.</note> 
               <hi>The Backſlider in heart shall be filled with his own ways.</hi> And the fooliſh ſinner <hi>eat the fruit of his own doings, and be filled with his own counſells.</hi>
               <note place="margin">23 Numb. 32.</note> And their calamity be ſo remarkable, that <hi>their ſin shall find them out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome peculiar puniſhments that ordinarily attend ſome ſort of crimes: that follow the guilty perſons almoſt as conſtantly as giddineſs doth a drunkard, as that the ſpoiler ſhall be ſpoiled, he that defrauds others, ſhall be outwitted, the Lyar ſhall looſe his credit: the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious talebearer be blaſted in his reputation, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor be brought low: the proud be ſcorned, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd: and <hi>he that ſtops his ears againſt the cry of the poor,</hi> ſhall want a friend to ſuccour him in diſtreſſe, <hi>ſhall cry himſelf and not be heard.</hi> That he that judgeth ſhall be judged: the ſlanderer be evil ſpoken of: that he that taketh the ſword ſhall periſh by the ſword: and that <hi>the Murderer ſhall not live out half his days.</hi> If <hi>Jacob</hi> deceive his old Father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> by the <hi>borrow'd garments</hi> of his Brother <hi>Eſaw;</hi> his own children, when he is old impoſe upon him by <hi>the bloudy garment</hi> of his beloved <hi>Joſeph. Abimelech</hi> ſlew ſeventy of his Brethren,
<note place="margin">6 Jud. 9.5: 6.</note> on one ſtone, and he himſelf was ſlaine by a piece of a mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. God ſometimes obſerves even an arithmetick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, demands, <hi>an eye for an eye,</hi> and <hi>a tooth for a tooth:</hi> gives <hi>bloud for bloud, and burning for burning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Jud. 9.6.</note> We have a pertinent example in <hi>Adonibezeck, who had his Thumbs and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37239:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>great Toes cutt off.</hi> And in the next verſe he owns that he had ſerved ſeventy Kings in the like manner. He was ſo affected with the equity and juſtice of his puniſhment, that he cries out,
<note place="margin">1 Ex 15.12. c. 29.14. c. 23.</note> 
               <hi>As I have done, ſo hath the Lord requited me. Pharoah</hi> reſolues to deſtroy the male <hi>infants</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and the <hi>firſtborn</hi> in every family of the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> was cut off in a night. He gives order to the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes that <hi>they</hi> ſhould be <hi>drownd,</hi> and he and his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hoſt periſht in the <hi>waters. Joſeph's Brethren</hi> ſold him into Aegypt, that his dream concerning <hi>their sheaves bowing down to his,</hi> might not be accomplisht, and that was the very means to bring it about. The Jews cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed the ſon of God, that the Romans might not come, &amp; take away their Land: and as the puniſhment of that crime, God ſends the <hi>Romans</hi> to deſtroy their Temple, citty, and Nation. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> thought to prevent the revolt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the <hi>King of Judah,</hi> by erecting <hi>calves</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> near to <hi>Sechem,</hi> (where the <hi>Samaritans</hi> had their Temple, and where <hi>Abraham</hi> built an altar) and forbidding the people to goe up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<note place="margin">2 Cron. 36.21.</note> and by that wretched policy he and his poſterity loſt the government of Iſrael. The captivity of Iſrael for <hi>ſeventy years</hi> was the punniſhment God inflicted for their prophaning the <hi>ſeventhday Sabbath,</hi> and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering their Lands to reſt every <hi>ſeventh year.</hi> The unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural luſt of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> we read was punniſht by <hi>fire from Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">19 Gen.</note> The puniſhment is in ſuch caſes the very
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37239:9"/>
               <hi>eccho</hi> of the ſin that brought it: Which honours the Juſtice of God, &amp; renders it conſpicuous to all obſervers. If <hi>Abſolon</hi> take a pride in his <hi>hair,</hi> his deſtruction ſhall come by that means. If <hi>Nadab</hi> &amp; <hi>Abihu</hi> offer <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> to the Lord,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18: 9.</note> by fire ſhall they be conſum'd: <hi>as face anſwers to Face,</hi> ſo doth the <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the <hi>impiety,</hi> that brought it.
<note place="margin">10 Levit.</note> If <hi>David</hi> glory in the <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of his men of war; <hi>ſeventy thouſand</hi> ſhall be ſwept away by a <hi>peſtilence,</hi> to diminiſh the number: that he may ſee cauſe of <hi>humiliation</hi> in the matter of his <hi>pride.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſerved God with a <hi>divided heart,</hi> his Kingdom ſhall be <hi>divided,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings. 11: 30.</note> &amp; but a part of it deſcend to his poſterity. Becauſe the <hi>Iſraclites</hi> ſerved <hi>ſtrange Gods</hi> in their <hi>own</hi> land, God threatens that other Lords ſhould have dominion over them, &amp; <hi>they ſhould ſerve ſtrangers, in a land that was not their own.</hi> Thus ſome herbs bear the marks of thoſe parts of the body, to which, if ill affected, they are medicinal; ſo doth the puniſhment &amp; the calamity oftentimes deſcribe the ſin for which God ſends it. The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Temporal <hi>Croſſe</hi> is formed as it were out of that <hi>forbidden Tree</hi> wherby he offended, or rather like <hi>the croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries on it in capital Letters an account of the crime, for which he ſuffers. Tho many of <hi>God's judgments,</hi> I confeſs,
<note place="margin">36 Pſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>are of a great depth,</hi> paſt our ſounding, as to the grounds &amp; reaſons of them, yet in ſeveral of them <hi>his Righteouſneſs is as the great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> i: e. viſible &amp; apparent to the dulleſt eye.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There is ſometimes a Suitableneſs in reſpect of the quantity &amp; the meaſure.</hi> He that ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reap ſparingly, &amp; he that ſoweth plentifully, ſo doth he reap. which is true of evil actions as well as good: Impudent &amp; extraordinary ſinners ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> been ſignalized by as remarkable judgments &amp; plagues from Heaven. <hi>God lays judgment to the line, &amp; equity to the Ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> rewards them according to their works, &amp; <hi>meaſureth</hi> out their calamities &amp; ſorrows in proportion to their ſins. Tho ſentence be not all ways ſpeedily executed againſt great offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37239:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; ſometimes not at all in this world, but they are bound over to the laff <hi>Great Aſſize</hi> in the world to come: yet in all ages divine juſtice giues ſome inſtances how notorious &amp; exemplary ſinners have had as extraordinary punniſhments.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is ſrequently a proportion &amp; reſemblance between the ſin &amp; the Punishment in reſpect of <hi>Time. In that very hour,</hi> when <hi>Belshazar</hi> was quaffing &amp; carowſing in the veſſells of the Temple, with his Princes, his Wives, &amp; Concubines; &amp; prayſing the Gods of gold &amp; ſilver, the hand of the Lord was againſt him,
<note place="margin">5 Dan. 3-6.</note> &amp; he ſaw his Doom written on the wall; which made his countenance fall, &amp; his Thoughts tremble, &amp; the joynts of his loyns were looſed, &amp; his knees ſmote one againſt an other. When <hi>Benhadad the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> with the 32 Kings with him, were drinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs drunk in the Pavilions,
<note place="margin">1 Kings. 20. c. 16: 19. v.</note> the young men of the Princes of the Provinces of <hi>Samaria,</hi> came out againſt them, &amp; ſlew every man his man, &amp;c. <hi>Jonah</hi> is purſued by a <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> at that very Time, <hi>when he fled from the Commandment of God.</hi> Many who have been going out of God's way, have been arreſted &amp; ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome ſtrange rebuke of divine Providence: wherin the Circumſtance of <hi>Time</hi> hath been peculiarly remarkable.</p>
            <p>God ſent the Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> to <hi>Ninive,</hi> that exceeding great City,
<note place="margin">3 Jon. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of three days journey,</hi> to deliver his terrible meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to that People: but he disobey'd his voice, &amp; fled to <hi>Tarshish.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 c. 3. v.</note> For which God condemned him to be <hi>three days</hi> a Priſoner in the belly of <hi>a great Fish.</hi> The word <hi>whale</hi> is not in the original Hebrew, or ſeptuagint Greek.</p>
            <p>The Jewish captivity for <hi>ſeventy years</hi> in <hi>Babilon,</hi> is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the prophanati on of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as one principal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking cauſe, as will appear by comparing thes following Scriptures, 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 36. <hi>c.</hi> 17. — 22. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 18: 17. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 27: 22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. <hi>c.</hi> 38: 46. 't was at the time of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> put to death <hi>the Lord of Glory;</hi> &amp;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37239:10"/>afterward about the ſame time of the year, <hi>the wrath of God came upon them to the uttermoſt</hi> for that ſin: their Temple, City, &amp; Nation were deſtroy'd by the <hi>Romans. Nebucadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> was admonisht of his <hi>Pride,</hi> &amp; warned of that Judgment which afterwards befell him: And as the Punnishment in its kind was proportioned to his ſin, (his Brutish condition being a ſuitable Rebuke for his inſolence &amp; vain glory,) the <hi>Time</hi> alſo of the execution of that Judgment is obſervable; it was juſt <hi>a twelve moneth</hi> from Daniel's interpretation of his dream concerning it,
<note place="margin">4 Dan. 29: 30: 31. v. 12 Acts. 32 Exod.</note> &amp; took effect while the proud words were in his mouth, <hi>Is not this great Babilon that I have built, by the might of my power, &amp; for the honour of my majeſty?</hi> So in the caſe of <hi>Herod:</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Iſraëlites,</hi> in the caſe of the <hi>molten calf.</hi> Your own reading &amp; obſervation may furnish you with exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Blaſphemers, Swearers, Lyars, Murderers, &amp; <hi>Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers</hi> &amp;c. who have been either punisht in the act; or have been follow'd by ſome perticular judgment afterwards, at the ſame time of the <hi>year,</hi> the ſame <hi>day</hi> of the <hi>moneth,</hi> or <hi>week</hi> or <hi>hour</hi> of the day, when they committed the ſin. So that the very <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of their calamity, hath brought the ſin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance for which they ſuffered. Several Villages, Towns, &amp; Cities, have been taken notice of, to have ſuffered greatly by <hi>Fires, which broke out on the Lordsday,</hi> that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerved &amp; talk't of as infamous for the <hi>prophanation</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> more then other places, &amp; ſome of them forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of ſuch Judgments for that very Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Oftentimes they meet with ſome Rebuke &amp; Punishment in the <hi>ſame Place,</hi> where they commit their folly. As in that very houſe where <hi>Rahab</hi> hid the <hi>Hebrew ſpies,</hi> she &amp; her kindred were afterward preſerved, as the Reward of her Faith: So di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Judgment doth frequently overtake men, in the very <hi>place</hi> where they acted their Wickedneſs.
<note place="margin">10 Levit. 1: 2.</note> 
               <hi>Nadab</hi> &amp; <hi>Abihu</hi> are deſtroied by Fire from Heaven <hi>before the Lord,</hi> where they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37239:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtrange fire, &amp; they are ſaid to dye <hi>before the Lord.</hi> How often doth the Drunkard get his death in the ſame houſe, where he drank to Exceſs, by cauſleſs quarrelling? And the Adulterer loos his Life in the ſame room, where he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Folly? <hi>Ahab,</hi> by the advice of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> murders Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Naboth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings. 21. c. v. 13. v. 19. c. 22. v. 38.</note> &amp; his ſons: but the Lord had ſaid, that <hi>in the ſame place, where Dogs lickt the bloud of</hi> Naboth, <hi>shall Dogs lick thy Bloud, even thine.</hi> Which was not long after exactly full filled, in a Place of the ſame nature. A publick &amp; common place, within the Territory of <hi>Samaria,</hi> but becauſe of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,
<note place="margin">2 Kings. 9. c. v. 23.</note> it was more literally &amp; expreſly accomplisht in the death of his ſon <hi>Joram.</hi> Who was ſlaine by <hi>Jehu,</hi> &amp; <hi>caſt into the ſame plat of ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 33.34. &amp;c.</note> to remaine unburied, as a prey for Dogs, <hi>according to the word of the Lord.</hi> And of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> for the ſame crime, ſpake the Lord, ſaying, <hi>The Dogs shalleat Jezabell, by the wall of Jezreel.</hi> Which was exactly verified.</p>
            <p>This illuſtrates the Juſtice of God, &amp; makes it conſpicuous to every Eye. As Publick <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> condemn notorious <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals</hi> to be executed <hi>at</hi> or <hi>near the place,</hi> where the Fact was committed. That the very <hi>Place</hi> may make the <hi>Sin</hi> to be the better Remembred, &amp; render the Equity of the ſentence the more manifeſt &amp; obſervable.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We are to conſider <hi>thoſe temporal Punishments of ſin; which flow from the ſins themſelus.</hi> that are either <hi>inſeparable from,</hi> or doe <hi>commonly attend &amp; follow them.</hi> Such as thes which follow,</p>
            <p>§. 1. <hi>Shame.</hi> Aſſoon as our firſt Parents had ſinned, as if the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the forbidden fruit had got into their faces, they <hi>blusht &amp; were ashamed</hi> of their nakedneſs, &amp; of their folly which brought it. And is it not in ſome meaſure thus, with their poſterity alſo? Such an inſeparable <hi>Shame</hi> is the fruit of ſin, that hardly any man will own himſelf guilty of the practice of any vice, till he hath changed its name: given it an honourable title, &amp; varniſht it with ſome appellative of vertue: that ſo <hi>prudence</hi> &amp; <hi>wiſdom,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37239:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>thrift</hi> &amp; <hi>good huſbandry, friendſhip</hi> &amp; <hi>good humour, valour</hi> &amp; <hi>generoſity,</hi> may protect <hi>worldlineſs, covetouſneſs, debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery,</hi> &amp; <hi>fooliſh mirth,</hi> &amp; conceal <hi>madneſs, fury,</hi> &amp; <hi>pride.</hi> The like may be ſaid of other faults. If men are ſurprized in ſome acts of Impiety, what ſilly excuſes will they frame? what childiſh pretences, &amp; frivolous eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions will they make? what ſlender ſhifts &amp; weak apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, to juſtifie them ſelv's, to extenuate, or prevent the publication of their folly? <hi>their diſordered,</hi> &amp; <hi>down caſt looks, or ſtupid ſilence,</hi> make it evident they are aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The ſhame of being thought guilty makes them ſhift, &amp; turn, &amp; try all methods, to excuſe them ſelv's, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend what they have done: &amp; ſo throw the blame on ſome what els, as on the temperament &amp; conſtitution of their bodies which they cannot help, on the importunities of their Company which they could notreſiſt, on the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Devil; or rather then fail, with <hi>Adam,</hi> they'l charge God himſelf as acceſſory to their crimes, and reflect upon his holy Providence. Except among a few Savages like beaſts, there is no nation or people under heaven where filthineſs, and intemperance, &amp; ſome groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſins, are not reckon'd <hi>ſhamefull.</hi> The voice of nature it ſelf is againſt ſuch ſins, and we therby violate the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty of our own natures, and offend againſt an internal witneſs that condemns us. And when once we begin to do ſo, God may leave us to proceed, till we become <hi>publick ſpectacles of ſhame</hi> to all that know us, and wiſh us
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37239:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>better. There are very few I hope who have ſin'd them ſelv's beyond all ſhame; tho more of late then ever, who <hi>work all uncleanneſs with greedineſs,</hi> and <hi>glory in their ſhame.</hi> Who boaſt of that which ſhould cover them with confuſion of face; but ſuch have ſinn'd them ſelv's within a ſtep of Hell; and being <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> are ſo far paſt all hope of being reclaim'd. None but ſuch <hi>Abſolons</hi> would commit lewdneſs <hi>on the houſe top,</hi> in the face of the ſun, and the view of the world. <hi>Tis a ſhame</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">5 Eph. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>to ſpeak of what ſome men do in ſecret.</hi> I wiſh ſuch ſins were ſecret ſtill, <hi>which were not then ſo much as to be named among Saints. i: e.</hi> not without need, and not without abhorrence. <hi>They that are drunk,</hi> ſaith the ſame Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>are drunk in the night.</hi> The Heathens them ſelv's never celebrated the feaſts of a drunken <hi>Bacchus,</hi> but by night. So for uncleannes, <hi>The eye of the Adulterer waiteth for the twilight,
<note place="margin">24 Job. 14:15:16.</note> ſaying no eye shall ſee me, and he disguiſeth his face, in the dark they dig throthouſes, which they had marked for themſelv's in the day time: they know not the light. For the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to them even as the ſhadow of death: if one know them, they are in the terrors of the shadow of death.</hi> So for murder, and theft and other <hi>works of Darkneſs,</hi> to which <hi>ſhame</hi> is inſeparably annext. How ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully are men disfigured by <hi>Drunkeneſs,</hi> How do thy talk and act like fools, when wine hath fill'd them with more Spirits then they are able to govern? how ill favor'd are their looks? and how ridiculous their carriage? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37239:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>that folly in their drunken fits which afterwards they are aſhamed to think or ſpeak of, expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>pitty</hi> of their friends &amp; neighbours, to the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of children, and the <hi>ſcorn</hi> of their own ſervants. T'is ſad to conſider how the commonneſs of this, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vices hath in great meaſure taken off the shame of committing it. So that we may ask the queſtion with the Prophet, <hi>Were they aſhamed, when they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all theſe abominations?</hi> and make the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>No, they were not at all ashamed, neither did they blush.</hi> If ever they reform, and return to God with all their hearts, they will then be heartily aſhamed,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E del mio vaneggiar vergogna e'l frutto,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E'l Pentirſi, e'l conoſcer chiaramente,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Che que quanto piace al mondo, è breve ſogno.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </note> when reflecting on their paſt folly, they ſhall aſk them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelv's, <hi>what fruit have we of thoſe things wherof we are now ashamed?</hi> But if a timely repentance do not bring them to holy ſhame and confuſion of face before they dye; <hi>they ſhall ariſe</hi> againe <hi>to shame and everlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 2. <hi>The paine, and trouble, and ſlavery, and ſufferings, that wait upon ſin,</hi> do correct and reprove the ſinner. And this will appear if we conſider 1. the preparatories to the commiſſion of ſome crimes. 2.
<note place="margin">12 Dan. 2.</note> The actual commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37239:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. The conſequent trouble by diſaponitment. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The preparations neceſſary to the commiſsion of ſome ſins.</hi> They who have had any tolerable education in the knowledg of Chriſtianity under Religious or ſober Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents cannot preſently adventure upon great Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. They muſt firſt ſtifle their convictions, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch their reaſon, and baffle conſcience, and lay aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de conſideration and ſerious thoughts, forſake the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the word, neglect the reading of the Bible and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good books, leave off ſecret prayer, entertaine looſe company, and admit ſome principles of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> or <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceiſm,</hi> before they can date to adventure. For the debauching of a young man well educated, is not to be done all at once; it is a work of ſome time, and muſt be effected by degrees, and many arts of the Devil are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in order to it. And after all, t'is with reluctance at firſt, that they dare do as others, &amp; run into the ſame exceſs of riot. And ſome groſſer villanies they bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle at ſtill, and are afraid to proceed. T'is a ſtrange expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Pſalmiſt, (7 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.) <hi>They Travel with Iniquity, and conceive miſchief:</hi> are in as great pain almoſt as a woman in travell, and all this, <hi>to bring forth a Lye.</hi> The Law of God ſtares them in the face, and ſomething within tells them. It is better to forbear, and they ought to do otherwiſe: ſo that they are not eaſy, or free from diſtracting fears, till the way be prepared by leſſer ſins, and a gradual Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37239:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">2. We may conſider <hi>the trouble they meet with in the actual commiſsion of ſome ſins.</hi> Not only as the demands of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral luſts are contradictory and inconſiſtent, and <hi>Satan</hi> in ſuch a caſe <hi>muſt needs caſt out Satan,</hi> becauſe all cannot be gratifyed: but <hi>the very act</hi> of ſome crimes <hi>is a down right punniſhment.</hi> So that with equal reaſon a man might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a feaver, or choos to be ſcorcht upon the fire; to quench his thirſt with his own ſweat. One man eats out his own heart with <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>malice,</hi> to ſee his neighbour proſper: another burns with <hi>impatient luſt,</hi> and cannot meet with the opportunity to acompliſh his laſcivious deſign. A nother is even <hi>choakt</hi> to death with <hi>thirſt for gold,</hi> and yet he <hi>labours in the fire,</hi> and cannot reach that eſtate he <hi>covets.</hi> Or if he do, he is ſtill as far from true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſatisfaction as he was before; yea <hi>farther,</hi> becauſe his drought increaſeth, his feaver grows upon him: the more he hath, the more he thinks is neceſſary to make him happy: like the <hi>horsleech,</hi> he will ſtill be crying, <hi>Give, Give,</hi> till the diſeas be cured. Moreover, to bring about a wicked purpoſe what pains do ſome men take, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive the model, to remove difficulties and objections, to obviate Rivals, and prevent disapointment, ſurprize, and diſcovery? what mean things muſt they ſtoop to? what baſe ſubmiſſions muſt they undergo? into how many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſhapes muſt they be transformed? and into what an agony do they put themſelv's? their countenance al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, their eyes fiery, their hands trembling, their breath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37239:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhort, and the whole man, body and ſoul, in diſorder. Wheras it were comparatively very <hi>eaſy,</hi> &amp; the way plaine, to keep in the path of righteouſneſs, and obey God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may conſider <hi>the conſequent trouble upon the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate commiſsion.</hi> The uneaſineſs &amp; remorſe of a natural conſcience, and the fruſtration of their hopes, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment falling ſhort of what they promis'd themſelv's, &amp; eagerly expected. They look't for <hi>pleaſure</hi> and they meet with <hi>diſquiet,</hi> from the reflexions of their own minds on their diſapointment, and a conſciouſneſs to themſelv's that they have not done well. They promiſed themſelv's <hi>eaſe,</hi> and meet with <hi>disſatisfaction.</hi> What they ſought for, they do not find; but inſtead of their expected joy, regret; conſcience threatens them with an after reckoning: to ſtop its mouth, and ſilence its clamours, they have recours to company, &amp; fresh pleaſures: &amp; being weary of one ſort, they muſt change for another, by various methods endeavoring, tho in vaine, to appeas their boſome enemy. But more of this under <hi>another head.</hi> And is it not a ſhame, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what <hi>pains</hi> men take to be <hi>undone,</hi> what <hi>Gibeonites</hi> they are in the <hi>Devil's ſervice?</hi> while we are ſuch <hi>lazy dreamers</hi> in the <hi>ſervice</hi> of <hi>God; whoſe yoke is eaſy, and whoſe burden is light.</hi> What and how many are the cares and fears, and difficulties of the <hi>Proud,</hi> and <hi>Ambitious?</hi> (who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may take it ill I began not with <hi>him</hi> firſt,) to be filled with the <hi>wind;</hi> and applauded by the people, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37239:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the world? how jealous of every Rival; how watchfull of every advantage; &amp; how diligent to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and make the moſt of it. When the favor of God, that is infinitely preferable, may be had at a che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aper rate. Why ſhall not <hi>we mind the things above,</hi> &amp; our future intreſt, with the <hi>ſame eagerneſs,</hi> that <hi>ſinners</hi> do the ſatisfaction of a <hi>ſenſual luſt?</hi> why ſhall not <hi>we ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve</hi> to enter into Heaven, with the <hi>ſame diligence</hi> as <hi>others</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to the Gates of <hi>Hell?</hi> why ſhall not <hi>we ſeek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God,</hi> and its righteouſneſs, with <hi>equal vigor</hi> and <hi>reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> the injoyment of a <hi>forbidden pleaſure?</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſince inſtead of paine, and trouble, ſorrow &amp; diſſatisfaction, which they meet with; <hi>the joy of the Lord would be our ſtrength,</hi> incouragement, and ſupport. For even <hi>in,</hi> as well as <hi>after, the keeping his commandments, there is great reward.</hi> His burden would be lighter too, the more we are accuſtom'd to bear it: &amp; his yoke eaſier, the longer we have carried it.</p>
            <p>§. 3. <hi>Sin corrects the ſinner in this world, by ſpoiling that peace, &amp; concord, that love, and unity, among men and Chriſtians, which is neceſſary to our temporal happineſs.</hi> Whence come wars ſightings, tumults &amp; diſorders, animoſities &amp; diviſions, quarrells &amp; contentions, but from luſt in the heart, &amp; the fruits of it in the life? from what other original can we derive the unchriſtian heats and janglings, ſtrifes and perſecutions, among Profeſſors; the uncharitable fewds and hatred among neighbours,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37239:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>unneceſſary</hi> &amp; <hi>tedious law ſuits,</hi> and the conſequent malice and contumelies of vexatious quarrelling, on which the impoveriſhing of particular perſons, and the ruine of whole families, is ſo often conſequent? did we but obſerve the Chriſtian rules of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> &amp; <hi>charity, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp; <hi>humility;</hi> did we but indeavor, <hi>as much as in us lays to live peaceably with all men; being kindly affectioned one towards another;</hi> apt to be reconciled, and ready to forgive, reſtraining our exorbitant paſſions, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting every thing of each other in the beſt ſens; with how different a face would the world appear, how happy would be the nation, the citty, the family, where the caſe were thus. But what contentions and enmities are cauſed every day by <hi>Pride, drunkenneſs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Evilſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king?</hi> in every town, village, and neighbourhood, we might find Inſtances. Were it not for the corruption of mankind, and the ſad effects of that, there were no foundation in any ſens to call <hi>the ſtate of Nature the ſtate of War.</hi> And the peace and harmony, and conſequent hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the world had not been deſtroy'd, but by the ſin of man. What Nation was ever ſet on fire within it ſelf or made deſolate by a forreign power; what battell was ever fought, (much leſs a Duel,) what war was ever commenc't or proſecuted, but on one ſide or the other or both, <hi>Ambition,</hi> or <hi>Pride, Raſhneſs,</hi> or <hi>Rebellion, Fury,</hi> or <hi>Revenge</hi> was at the bottom? hence they ſpring as from their grand <hi>ſource,</hi> by thes were they cheriſht as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37239:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>by their proper <hi>fuel:</hi> the great <hi>convulſions</hi> &amp; <hi>deſolations</hi> that tear <hi>Provinces</hi> &amp; <hi>Empires,</hi> and deſtroy <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> are cauſed by <hi>armies</hi> of <hi>Iniquities</hi> rather then of <hi>ſoldiers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">13 Pr. 10.</note> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, contention and war, are the ſcumm of <hi>pride.</hi> Wheras, <hi>the meek ſhall inherit the earth,</hi> and be delighted <hi>with multitudes of Peace.</hi> Among the ſinleſs <hi>Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">37 Pſ. 11.</note> tho there be many <hi>Legions,</hi> we read of no <hi>wars.</hi> The <hi>Earth</hi> only is the ſeat of <hi>war; Jeruſalem above is free.</hi> If men would <hi>ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well, Spears</hi> muſt <hi>be turned into ploughs hears, and ſwords into pruning hooks.</hi> And <hi>the inhabitants of the earth would learn war no no more,</hi> did they once forbear to be <hi>wicked. Princes</hi> would not then oppreſs and murder their <hi>Subjects;</hi> nor would <hi>Subjects</hi> rebel againſt their lawfull <hi>Souveraigns;</hi> a bleſſed uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal <hi>peace</hi> would return to the <hi>earth,</hi> which is now ſo much a ſtranger to the far greateſt part of the inhabited world. So that the <hi>Reproof</hi> and <hi>Correction of ſin</hi> thunders in our ears by the <hi>noiſe of canon,</hi> and the Inſtruments of war; is as <hi>loud</hi> as the <hi>beating of Drums,</hi> and the ſound of <hi>trumpets:</hi> it ſhould peirce our hearts, as do the laſt <hi>cries</hi> of mangled <hi>ſoldiers:</hi> and affect us with a like reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as do the tragical effects of a deſolateing War.</p>
            <p>§. 4. <hi>Sin doth correct and reprove the ſinner in this world, by impoveriſhing his Eſtate.</hi> Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs and Luſt, Ambition and Pride, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Quarrelling, Prodigality, the Gameing humour,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37239:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp;c. have all a tendency to <hi>Poverty,</hi> and commonly effect it. If men will <hi>ſell themſelves to commit wickedneſs,</hi> they muſt <hi>ſell their eſtates,</hi> to make proviſion for their luſts. The <hi>Drunkard and the glutton ſhall come to poverty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">23 Pr. 21.</note> and <hi>Idleneſs cloth a man with rags. He that loveth pleaſure shall be poor.
<note place="margin">21 Pr. 17.28. c. 19.</note> And he that loveth wine, &amp; oyl, ſhall not be rich. And he that follows after vaine perſons, ſhall have poverty enough.</hi> Such men are not only unfitted for the works of their calling, wherby they ſhould ſubſiſt; but will <hi>pawn</hi> all they <hi>have, borrow</hi> all they <hi>can,</hi> and <hi>ſell</hi> all they are <hi>worth,</hi> to maintaine their vices. They mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend their time, and neglect their Imployments, which would otherwiſe find them a lively-hood, and ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty comes upon them ere they are aware. For no man reſolves from a vaſt eſtate to make himſelf a <hi>Beggar;</hi> but at the long run how many do ſo? <hi>this needleſs expence</hi> is for their <hi>honour,</hi> or rather <hi>pride;</hi> and will not undoe them: <hi>that</hi> is for their <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>diverſion;</hi> and they think they may bear it, it will not ruine them: and ſo for others, no one of which alone brings <hi>poverty,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in a little time do it. What large revenues have been waſted in <hi>vanity?</hi> how many conſiderable patrimonies devoured by <hi>luſt?</hi> men that had eſtates left them, almoſt ſufficient to maintaine an <hi>army,</hi> have been <hi>begger'd</hi> by a ritious courſe, and made as indigent as a <hi>disbanded foot ſoldier;</hi> reduced to a morſell of bread, and deprived of neceſſaries, and forc't to depend on thoſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37239:16"/>who were once their dependants. It would be endleſs to give <hi>a bill of all the coſt and charges,</hi> which ſome men are at, to maintaine and feed their luſts. How many have been forc't to <hi>feed on huſks,</hi> and ready to ſtarve, as the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> by following his luſtfull and riotous courſes. They that have gliſtered in <hi>ſcarlet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Lam. 5.</note> have by this means <hi>imbrac't dunghills.</hi> Great eſtates have been turn'd into <hi>ſawce,</hi> to pleas a <hi>glutton,</hi> and he that once far'd deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly every day, was choice in his dyet, and delicate in his food, and prodigal in his treats and intertainments, is at a loſſe where to find a din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>His throat</hi> was <hi>an open ſepulcher,</hi> and his houſes, lands, and livings, and money too, have been buried in <hi>this tomb.</hi> So for other ſins, <hi>the poor and the Deceitfull man ſhall meet together</hi> i: e. the <hi>latter</hi> be brought as low, as mean, and miſerable, and indigent as the <hi>former.</hi> What the oppreſſor wrings from the Fatherleſs and wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, or gets by over reaching his neighbours,
<note place="margin">29 Pr 13.</note> thro the little arts of <hi>cheating,</hi> which are called the <hi>myſteries of Trade,</hi> ſhall be <hi>put into a bag with holes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Hag. 6.</note> And methinks this reproof of ſin ſhould be very audible and affecting, that you cannot loos your ſouls, throw away your hopes of Heaven, and be miſerable and undone for ever, but you muſt part with your <hi>money</hi> too, and be begger'd here on earth. I might add under this head, that <hi>ſin doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh the ſinner by conſuming his precious Time.</hi> God gives us other bleſſings with a larger hand, in a greater
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37239:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>plenty and abundance at once: only our <hi>Time</hi> he diſtills by drops; and <hi>never gives us two moments at once,</hi> but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes away <hi>one,</hi> when he lends us <hi>another.</hi> To teach us the price of ſo rich a Jewel. And what opinion have ſick and dyeng perſons of the worth and value of their <hi>irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable Time,</hi> which we prodigally conſume in ſin and folly: in vaine company, and ſinfull mirth; in ſenſual pleaſures, and diverſions; with the neglect of the great end and buſineſs, we ought to proſecute in <hi>this Life,</hi> in order to the felicity of the next. Forgetting that we haſten dayly to <hi>the end of time,</hi> and our <hi>final judgment,</hi> &amp; that wither we ſleep or wake; wither we work, or are Idle; wither we prepare for death, and judgment, and our Everlaſting ſtate, or do it not; our glaſs runs, and we are haſtning to our laſt hour. Oh that we would think, with ſerious <hi>ſelf-Reflexions,</hi> what deſpairing ſouls beyond the grave would give for ſome of that <hi>Time,</hi> we know not what to do with, but ſpend in vanity, or what is worſe! or what we our ſelus ſhal ere long be willing to give for a little of it upon the ſame terms as now, when time is paſt, and t'is too late.</p>
            <p>§. 5. <hi>Sin doth correct and reprove the ſinner in this Life, by blaſting his Reputation.</hi> There muſt be ſome <hi>appearance</hi> at leaſt of <hi>vertue,</hi> and <hi>goodneſs,</hi> of <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>honeſty,</hi> to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any thing <hi>honourable,</hi> and recommend it as <hi>praiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi> The groſſer acts of <hi>wickedneſs</hi> are almoſt every where
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37239:17"/>acounted of <hi>ill repute,</hi> hence it is that few arrive to that height of impudence and degeneracy, as to rail and ſpeak evil of others for being <hi>upright</hi> and <hi>religious,</hi> being <hi>honeſt men</hi> and <hi>good Chriſtians,</hi> but for being <hi>Hypocrites:</hi> for pretending to <hi>be</hi> what they are <hi>not:</hi> practical religion, and the power of godlineſs hath ſtill ſuch an <hi>invincible awe</hi> upon the minds of men, and commands that reſpect and inward <hi>reverence,</hi> which they cannot refuſe. So true is it, that <hi>they who honour God, ſhall be honoured.</hi> And t'is equally certaine and univerſal, that <hi>they who deſpiſe and forſake him, ſhall be lightly eſteem'd.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> And we find by experience, that men expoſe themſelv's to <hi>contempt,</hi> &amp; loos their reputation by forſakeing God. <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs</hi> cloud the reaſon, and weaken the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, corrupt the judgment, and deſtroy wisdom, and render men not only an <hi>abomination</hi> to God, and his holy Angels, but the <hi>contempt</hi> or <hi>pitty</hi> of all wiſe and ſober men. Their vices make them <hi>vile,</hi> Ecclips the glory of their birth, and the honour which their anceſtors, and families, or their own other good qualities would give them. The name of a <hi>Liar</hi> is a brand of <hi>disgrace,</hi> and a mark of <hi>dishonour,</hi> among the worſt of men who often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſo far, as to demand his bloud for reparation of the <hi>affront,</hi> who preſumed to call them ſo. Sin, ſayth a late Author, as ſome beaſts, hath a ſtinking breath, as well as deadly claws, and brings infamy and disgrace, as well as paine and trouble. If men degrade themſelves into
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37239:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſwine</hi> by Intemperance, or into <hi>goats</hi> by laſciuiouſneſs, &amp; luſt, they muſt not expect the reward of vertue, to be well reputed, and ſpoken of. If they are <hi>ſlaves</hi> to an Imperious luſt, they muſt bear the <hi>Infamy</hi> of being ſo. And no better are they in the practice of Impiety: for as <hi>Slaves</hi> are at the command of their Maſters, and blindly obey their wills, and are no gainers by what they do, and oftentimes feel the laſh and the whip, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their <hi>drudgery;</hi> ſuch is the caſe of ſinners, under the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of a <hi>domineering vice.</hi> Yea their <hi>ſervice</hi> is more <hi>dirty,</hi> and <hi>dishonourable,</hi> their <hi>chains ſtronger,</hi> and their <hi>recovery</hi> more <hi>difficult,</hi> as being <hi>leſs apprehenſive</hi> &amp; <hi>ſenſible</hi> of their <hi>thraldom.</hi> And who can <hi>honour</hi> or <hi>eſteem</hi> ſuch voluntary <hi>ſlaves,</hi> under the worſt of <hi>Tyrants?</hi> they render themſelv's <hi>infamous</hi> &amp; <hi>deſpicable;</hi> &amp; can not expect better then to be <hi>ſcorned,</hi> or <hi>pittied.</hi> No man will eſteem or truſt one that is a <hi>known drunkard,</hi> and <hi>whoremaſter:</hi> a frugal honeſt man that hath but half the eſtate, is better lov'd, &amp; will be farther truſted, then ſuch a one, tho he have twice as much. Who can think or ſpeak well of a <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard</hi> any otherwiſe then of a cask or veſſell to be often filled and emptied. As of one that is a confident boaſter of himſelf, his own actions &amp; undertakings: a ſlanderer &amp; backbiter of others; one that is vaine and ſcandalous in company, foolishly babling all he knows, unfaithfully revealing the ſecrets of his friends, raſh and haſty in his reſolutions; extravagant in his projects, irregular in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37239:18"/>his actions; &amp;c. And what reputation can ſuch a man expect? the like I might ſay of the <hi>Glutton,</hi> who ſpends his Life in carrying meat from the <hi>Table</hi> to the <hi>Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill;</hi> and ſo of others. <hi>The name of ſuch men ſhall rot,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man. It ſhall putrifie <hi>aſſoon</hi> as their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſometimes long <hi>before.</hi> Yea ſome mens wickedneſs makes them <hi>infamous after they are dead,</hi> kills them to immortality, and poyſons their memory to future ages: they ſtand upon record as great Villains, and warnings to poſterity.</p>
            <p>§. 6. <hi>Sin corrects and reproves the ſinner in this world by deſtroying his health.</hi> How doth gluttony and drunkenneſs correct men by evening vomits, and morning qualms, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the ſtomach, pains of the head, and inflammations of the liver, rheums, gouts, dropſies, cholick, conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, apoplexies, palſies, decay of ſight, want of appetite, loſſe of memory, and judgment: ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeing the braine, weakning all the members of the body, and haſtening old age and death? How many an healthy conſtitution hath been deſtroyed by intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? beſides that it inflames paſſion, and excites quarrells, makes men more apt to give affronts, &amp; more unwilling to take them. On which acount ſaith Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>Who hath wo, who hath ſorrow,
<note place="margin">23 Pr 29.</note> who hath wounds without cauſe? they that tarry long at the wine &amp;c.</hi> who can recount all the miſchiefs to the body, by an exceſs of eating and drinking? wheras abſtinence and a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37239:19"/>life hath been proved by many to be the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cure of catarrhs, and gouts, and other diſeaſes, wherwith formerly they have been tormented. How many miſerable inſtances have we known, of men tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd by <hi>acute diſtempers,</hi> ſwoln with <hi>gouts,</hi> burn't with <hi>feavers,</hi> rackt by the <hi>ſtone,</hi> torn with <hi>cholicks,</hi> &amp;c. and forc't to pine away a great part of their days in paine &amp; miſery, by the effects of Intemperance and luſt. By this means <hi>Princes and great men</hi> have been forc't to own, that <hi>it is an evil thing and a bitter,</hi> to forſake God, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch torments as the fruit of their Impieties, that have made them envy the condition of <hi>Peaſants, Slaves, and Beggars.</hi> How many ſacrifice their <hi>health,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength,</hi> to a beaſtly opportunity, and are puniſht by pains of the head; oppreſſions of the heart; conturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſtomach; gripeing of the bowells, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual thirſt; unſeaſonable and unquiet watchfullneſs; (when nature and digeſtion require reſt.) Beſides that <hi>horrible diſeaſe</hi> imparted by this vice, the moſt cruel, the moſt filthy, the moſt ſhamefull of all maladies: (from which no luſtfull perſon can be ſecure: Becauſe 'tis the nature of vice, and of this in perticular, to precipitate from one degree of exceſs to another.) A diſeas which anticipates the corruption and uncleanneſs of the grave; wherby ſinners meet with their <hi>Limbo,</hi> their <hi>Tophet</hi> here, as a ſad <hi>preface,</hi> without repentance to an <hi>everlaſting Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37239:19"/>
            <p>§. 7. <hi>By an untimely Death.</hi> 'Tis true a natural Death is the fruit of ſin, we may conſider epidemical diſeaſes, and our common mortality, the trouble of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the pains of dyeing, as ſome <hi>correction,</hi> and <hi>reproof of ſinners.</hi> Their tears and groans, and ghaſtly looks in a dyeing hour, their broken ſighs, their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted members, their trembling languiſhing pulſe, their putrid breath, and laſt agonies, do all beſpeak us to conſider what <hi>ſin</hi> hath done. But a <hi>natural</hi> death being the punniſhment of the firſt tranſgreſſion, and common to all mankind; 'tis an <hi>untimely death,</hi> I am now to ſpeak of.</p>
            <p>Without diſputeing <hi>wither the period of Life he muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or not,</hi> This is certaine, that God from the infinity of his nature muſt needs be preſent in all duration at once; and ſo cannot but foreſee and know how long we ſhall live. And t' is likewiſe evident from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reaſon, and experience,
<note place="margin">55 Pſ. 23.</note> that ſome do not <hi>live out half their days,</hi> to which they might have arriv'd according to the cours of nature. The meek, &amp; ſuch as are bleſſed of God, <hi>ſhall live long to inherit the earth, but the Transgreſſors ſhall be cutt off.
<note place="margin">37 Pſ. 22.</note> The fear of the Lord prolongeth days; but the years of the wicked ſhall be ſhortned.</hi> Some think that <hi>Balaam</hi> when he deſired <hi>to dye the death of the Righteous,</hi> and <hi>that his laſt end might be like his,</hi>
               <note place="margin">23 Numb. 10.</note> meant only the prevention of an <hi>untimely death,</hi> &amp; that he might goe to his grave in <hi>a good old age.</hi> And God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37239:20"/>hath promiſed, among other temporal bleſſings, that the good man ſhall be <hi>gathered in peace to his Fathers like a ſhok of corn fully ripe: and crown'd with length of days;</hi> as well as with riches and honour. T'is true a ſhort Life, and an haſty death, are not allways a <hi>curſe,</hi> or the fruit of God's diſpleaſure. To a prepared ſoul, t' is a bleſſing, and as ſuch more deſireable, then to <hi>abide in the flesh,</hi> in order to our <hi>being with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</hi> But how many are there whoſe impieties <hi>ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their days,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hinc ſubitae mortes, atque inteſtata ſenectus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It nova nec triſtis per cunctas fabula coenas:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ducitur iratis plaudendum funus amicis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </note> haſten their diſſolution. How many dye martyrs by the fire of luſt. <hi>By the ſtrange wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, many fall down wounded, and many ſtrong men are ſlaine by her. Her houſe is the way to the grave, &amp; leads to the chambers of death.</hi> How many have extinguiſht their vital flame, by intemperate drinking, and brought thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, or furniſht the matter of them, by exceſs, wherof in a ſhort time they dyed. Beſides the many thouſand <hi>Murders</hi> which <hi>drunkenneſs</hi> hath cauſed: in a drunken fit men have murdered themſelv's, their beſt friends, and deareſt Relations. The riſe of moſt <hi>duels</hi> hath been from hence: the challenge ſent from the tavern, or the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fighting commenc't there. Not to mention,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37239:20"/>what every <hi>ſeſsions</hi> and <hi>aſsize</hi> may inform us, how many expoſe themſelv's to the penalty of humane laws by great Transgreſſions, &amp; periſh by the ſword of the civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. Which may be conſidered as another inſtance, wherby Sin doth correct and reprove the Sinner in this world.</p>
            <p>§. 8. <hi>By troubleſome reflections, and horror of Conſcience.</hi> Rather then ſinners shall eſcape unpunniſht, they shall correct themſelv's: <hi>Conſcience</hi> that was privy to their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, &amp; keeps a regiſter of their crimes, &amp; is more then a thouſand witneſſes, shall accuſe, condemn, &amp; torture them, (&amp; that it may be for ſecret ſins, which none of their acquaintance can charge them with,) shall be <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Judge,</hi> and <hi>Executioner</hi> too, before their irreverſible doom at the day of judgment. Hence many are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually haunted by the <hi>Spectres</hi> of their former wickedneſs; &amp; their own guilty minds frequently check them in their greateſt jollity, and make a ſad diſcord in their mirth: ſo that <hi>in the midſt of laughter, their hearts are ſorrowfull.</hi> They are always uneaſy, and walk in fear, leaſt vengence over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them. As the firſt Murderer <hi>Cain,</hi> who was afraid of being <hi>ſlaine by every man he met,</hi> when he was ſure to meet with none, but <hi>Brethren</hi> &amp; <hi>Nephews.</hi> What can we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe should be able to give ſuch a man courage &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port? when he is dejected by his own fears, and caſt down by an inward ſens of guilt. They muſt needs have ſad hearts, not withſtanding chearfull countenances, from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37239:21"/>the biteings of this <hi>Tarantula</hi> within, which no outward applications will cure; any more then an inward bruiſe may be healed by a plaiſter upon the outer garment. Yea <hi>ſome</hi> from the <hi>horror</hi> of their own minds, have been ready to make away themſelv's, and become <hi>their own Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners;</hi> as if the <hi>Worm,</hi> which never dyes, were more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable then the <hi>fire,</hi> that never goes out. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the moſt ſharp &amp; terrible bodily pains are much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the anguiſh of an awakened guilty Conſcience, under the apprehenſions of divine wrath. Did you neuer hear the outcries of a dyeing ſinner, after an impenitent wicked Life, convinc't of ſin, &amp; ſenſible of Eternity, expecting within a few hours to appear before his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge? When his paſt Impieties ſtare him in the face, &amp; Death, and Hell, and Gods Eternal vengence, are open &amp; naked before him: Deſpairing now of the mercy of God, which all his Life before he ſlighted, and curſeing thoſe fugitive pleaſures, &amp; vaine Companions, that intic't him to miſpend his time, &amp; commit folly, and neglect his preparations for another world.</p>
            <p>But many ſinners feel theſe rebukes of Conſcience in <hi>health,</hi> as well as <hi>ſickneſs;</hi> Terrors poſſeſs their guilty minds, &amp; curdle all their delights. They tremble with torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fears, which they cannot get rid of: &amp; not takeing the right method of cure, they at laſt ſigh away their fainting breath, in <hi>total deſpair.</hi> In the mean time what arts do they uſe, to drive away <hi>this evil ſpirit,</hi> which perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37239:21"/>haunts them? but none of their tryed methods of run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to company, &amp; recreations, to drunkenneſs &amp; riot, &amp;c. have been found effectual for any conſiderable time. But ſtill they are dogged by their own guilt. In vaine do you think, to laugh &amp; ſport &amp; drink away your <hi>fears;</hi> they will ſoon return upon you with greater violence, when the company is broken up, &amp; the heat of wine is over: Which like ſprightly muſick may raiſe a mans mind for the preſent, but will leave him more dumpish &amp; melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly afterward. Yea it makes farther work for <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> &amp; ſo will but augment your <hi>terrors.</hi> Mirth &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, inſtead of giveing eas to an accuſing conſcience, will but aggravate and increas your trouble: you will ſpeed no better then the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> did, when they ſent for <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to make them ſport: who pull'd the houſe down upon their heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Backſliders,</hi> of all others, are perticularly reproved and corrected by ſin, in this inſtance: how many ſuch have been known, who when they come to themſelv's, and repent, are even <hi>diſtracted by the terrors of the Lord,</hi> thro remorſe for their <hi>apoſtacy?</hi> ſuch before Repentance have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pleaſure in the commiſſion of ſin then others, who never had ſo much light, or knew ſo much of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon workings of the Spirit: And afterwards have more terrible apprehenſions of God's avenging Juſtice. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſpeaks louder in their ears, and the flames of Hell flaſh oftener in their eyes. So that commonly they doubt,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37239:22"/>wither God will ever receive them to mercy; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wither they have not committed <hi>the unpardonable Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Backſliding Chriſtians,</hi> who have formerly rejoyc't in <hi>the light of God's countenance,</hi> and walk't in <hi>the comforts of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> (while they walk't in their <hi>Integrity</hi>) after the commiſſion of <hi>preſumptuous ſins,</hi> have dearly experienc't <hi>how evill &amp; bitter a thing it is, to forſake God.</hi> Conſcience flyes in their faces, being commonly awakened by ſome afflicting providence) and ſetts their ſins, with the aggravations of them, in order before them; and <hi>writes bitter things againſt them.</hi> All their joy is turned to worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and their very lives are become a burden, and yet they dare not dye. They read their <hi>Inditement,</hi> but cannot ſee a <hi>pardon,</hi> or ſcarce entertaine any hopes of <hi>one.</hi> They are covered as with <hi>ſackloth,</hi> and lay in the <hi>duſt,</hi> bewailing their folly, and confeſſing their guilt, with broken, bleeding hearts before the Lord. <q>Oh <hi>vile Apoſtate</hi> that I am! after ſuch a profeſſion for ſo long a time, after ſo many convictions of the evill of ſin, and ſo much experience of the ſweetneſs and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of holy walking, thus to forſake my own mercies, diſhonour my profeſſion, and provoke God.</q> 
               <hi>It had been better for me never to have known the way of Righteouſneſs, then after haveing known, and try'd it,</hi> thus ſhamefully to revolt. Such a mans <hi>ſin</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears with <hi>horror,</hi> and fills him with <hi>anguiſh:</hi> ſo that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37239:22"/>he would give all the world he had not been guilty of that apoſtacy he repents of. Lord! <hi>what a wretch, what a fool was I?</hi> will ſuch a man ſay, <hi>Thus willfully to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, in ſpight of the cleareſt knowledg, &amp; the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing kindneſs? againſt ſo many obligations, ſo many vows, &amp; reſolutions, thoſe made upon the moſt weighty reaſons: what grace, what love, what mercy, have I trampled on, &amp; ſinned againſt? whither ſhall I goe? what ſhall I doe? how dare I appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that God, on whom I have thus perfidiously turned my back! how can I ever hope to regaine his loſt favour! Againſt thee only, holy God, have I ſinned, &amp; done evill in thy ſight. Lord! I am unworthy to appear in thy preſence, I am ashamed &amp; bluſh to look up to Heaven. How ſhall I eſcape thy juſtice, when I have deſpis'd thy goodneſs, &amp; forfeited thy grace! What can I reply, if thou utterly forſake me, &amp; refuſe to be intreated by my prayers, or accept my return? Eternal wrath is my due,</hi> Hell <hi>is my deſerved portion: &amp; even</hi> there <hi>may I juſtly carry thes ſtings of conſcience; even</hi> there <hi>muſt I acknowledg I was juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned, &amp; punniſht; &amp; own the righteouſneſs of my doom, to unquenchable fire, with my flameing tongue &amp; breath. Wretch that I am, who ſhall deliver, &amp; ſave me! only the mercy of God, in Chriſt, whoſe bloud, cleanſeth from all ſin, can poſsibly relieve the exigence of my caſe. And wilt thou pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and pardon, and graciously receive ſuch a rebel? For Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, ſpare me, &amp; give me repentance; blot out my transgreſsion, for it is great, and hide thy face from my ſin, from</hi> my ſin, <hi>which is</hi> ever before me. <hi>I cannot avoid the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37239:23"/>ſight of it; I cannot but remember it, and abhorr my ſelf in duſt &amp; ashes, &amp; goe mourning all the day long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thes are the thoughts, this is the language of an humble Penitent, under the ſens of former backſlidings. To this purpoſe, <hi>David</hi> tells us in one of his penitentiall Pſalms,
<note place="margin">51 Pſ. 3.</note> that <hi>his ſin was ever before him.</hi> And in another, that <hi>his ſorrow was continually before him.</hi> The one as the <hi>cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">38 Pſ. 17.</note> the other as the <hi>effect.</hi> His <hi>ſin</hi> as the <hi>reaſon</hi> of his <hi>ſorrow;</hi> &amp; his <hi>ſorrow</hi> as the <hi>fruit</hi> of his <hi>ſin,</hi> was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>before him.</hi> This made him cry ſo earneſtly for pardon, <hi>O Lord, blot out my transgreſsions; and remember not my ſinns.</hi> i. e. I remember them, I acknowledg, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs them, they are ever in <hi>my view,</hi> &amp; <hi>before my face.</hi> O do not <hi>thou remember</hi> them, but caſt them <hi>behind thy back.</hi> On this account, he complains of <hi>broken bones,</hi> &amp; <hi>a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirit.</hi> That <hi>the arrows of God ſtuck faſt in his ſoul, and his hand preſſed him ſore:</hi> that <hi>he roared all the day long: &amp; watered his couch with his tears.</hi> Thes conflicts and terrors, this darkneſs &amp; deſpondency, are the fruit of backſliding, and t'is well if it do not iſſue in <hi>the ſin unto death,</hi> in final incurable Apoſtacy. T' is true ſome who are <hi>fallen</hi> from ſo great an height, are <hi>raiſed</hi> againe: and God upon ſincere Repentance will pardon and ſave returning Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders, yet <hi>ſo as by fire,</hi> with great difficulty. And they may never recover their former tranquillity and peace, but walk <hi>heavily and ſoftly,</hi> under doubts and fears, and dejection of ſpirit, to their dyeing day. And likewiſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37239:23"/>ſuffer <hi>ſmart Afflictions,</hi> to ſcour off the filth they have contracted by their revolt, and to humble them more deeply under the apphrehenſion of their agravated guilt. In <hi>thes,</hi> and <hi>other ſuch inſtances,</hi> as might be mentioned, <hi>ſin doth correct and reprove the ſinner in this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What remains, is to conſider what <hi>Inferences</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> &amp; <hi>duty,</hi> may be collected from the preceding diſcourſe, for our <hi>inſtruction</hi> and <hi>practiſe;</hi> or what <hi>improvement</hi> we ſhould make of it. Which I ſhall diſpatch in thes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing <hi>Propoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 1. <hi>That we ought thankfully to admire</hi> the <hi>wiſdom</hi> &amp; <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>God, who hath,</hi> in ſo great meaſure, <hi>connected our preſent duty &amp; happineſs.</hi> That we cannot diſobey God without injuring our ſelv's, &amp; feeling the ſmart of it, even in this Life. Let us thank him for <hi>hedging up</hi> our way to Eternal death, by the <hi>thorns</hi> &amp; <hi>briars</hi> of temporal calamities. By makeing ſin ſo unreaſonable, painfull, ſhameful, troubleſome, &amp; againſt our Intreſt, even on this ſide the <hi>Grave.</hi> In ſo much, that in many inſtances we can not be <hi>undone forever,</hi> without being <hi>miſerable now:</hi> nor loos the happineſs of the <hi>other world,</hi> without expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeing our ſelv's to many ſorrows, &amp; calamities in <hi>this.</hi> By our ſin &amp; folly we make the <hi>Rod</hi> which corrects us: our own finger twiſts the <hi>cords,</hi> wherby we are rebukt &amp; chaſtened: the <hi>web</hi> which inſnares &amp; intangles us is ſpun out of our own bowells. And God in wiſdom &amp; kindneſs ſo orders it, to prevent our perishing in both worlds.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37239:24"/>
            <p>§. 2. <hi>We ought hearthly to bleſs God for reſtraining us, by his grace, &amp; providence, from Preſumtuous Crimes.</hi> That he was pleas'd to ſtop us in our way to ruine, &amp; mercifully prevent us from running into thoſe exceſſes, which would have been attended with ſuch miſerable effects here, &amp; at laſt have expoſed us to his condemning ſentence. Had he not ſometimes <hi>withheld</hi> us by his <hi>grace,</hi> when we were tempted: &amp; <hi>prevented</hi> us, at other times, by his <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> from divers Temptations, by which others have fallen; we had ere this been deplorable <hi>ſpectacles</hi> of divine Juſtice, and ſeverely corrected by our own folly. And this is the favor, which God is pleaſed to vouchſafe to his <hi>Children,</hi> to ſuccor them when they are tempted, &amp; to keep them from ſuch Temptations, as they would not be able to reſiſt. Not that he is a <hi>good man,</hi> who would live wickedly, if he were but tempted to do ſo, by thoſe ordinary trials that humane nature may expect: but he who prefers God, and the bleſſedneſs of the other world, before all things els; &amp; lives agreable to ſuch a choice; if he ſo continue shall be ſaved: tho there might have been ſuppoſed a Temptation ſo ſtrong, as would have conquered his reſolutions, with that meaſure of Grace he then had, if it had not been fortified with new ſupplies. Therfore thank God for the care of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which ſecures us from many dangerous Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: &amp; for the aſſiſtance of his Grace in inabling us to come off wit victory, when we have been tryed.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37239:24"/>
            <p>§. 3. <hi>How much better</hi> then <hi>is a Life of holy Obedience to God, then the practice of ſin, if there were no reward to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted after Death?</hi> If in this Life only we had hope (the caſe of cruel <hi>perſecution</hi> excepted: ſuch as St. Paul ſpeaks of 1 Cor. 15. And <hi>extreme Poverty,</hi> &amp; <hi>bodily Pains,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe under <hi>thes</hi> the hopes of a future bleſſedneſs are the chief ſupports: otherwiſe) We ſhould be ſo far from being <hi>of all men the moſt miſerable</hi> in this world, by obeying the Goſpell of Chriſt; that t' is apparently for our <hi>preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt,</hi> to obſerve the precepts of natural &amp; Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: the Yoke of Chriſt is eaſier, &amp; his burden lighter, &amp; the ſervice of God leſs difficult, then the drudgery of Sin, with ſuch conſequences, as have been mentioned. Let me ſeriouſly appeal to your Experience, wither it be not <hi>evill</hi> &amp; <hi>bitter</hi> to depart from God, &amp; caſt off his fear? have you not found it ſo, to your coſt? have not you your ſelv's, &amp; many others whom you know, been ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>chaſtened</hi> &amp; <hi>reproved,</hi> by ſin? &amp; <hi>what fruit have</hi> you, or they, or what fruit have you ever <hi>had,</hi> of the ſins you are now <hi>ashamed</hi> of, but ſuch as hath been deſcribed? <hi>what profit hath he,</hi> ſaith the Wiſeman,
<note place="margin">5 Ecl. 16.</note> 
               <hi>who hath labor'd for the wind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bring in your <hi>acounts</hi> of what you have ever got by a wicked Live: &amp; compare it with the preſent reward of holy liveing. Set down your income, &amp; proceed to a reckoning, &amp; ſee what the total ſumme amounts to. So much <hi>Shame</hi> &amp; <hi>Fear;</hi> ſo much <hi>Care</hi> &amp; <hi>Trouble;</hi> ſo much
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37239:25"/>
               <hi>Loſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Damage;</hi> ſo much <hi>Ignominy</hi> &amp; <hi>Disgrace;</hi> ſo much <hi>Disquiet</hi> &amp; <hi>Disſatisfaction;</hi> ſo much <hi>Discredit</hi> &amp; <hi>Disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> ſo many <hi>Fruſtrations</hi> &amp; <hi>Disapointments;</hi> ſo many <hi>Difficulties</hi> &amp; <hi>perplexities;</hi> ſo many <hi>Diſeaſes, Griefs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aches.</hi> An <hi>ill name,</hi> an <hi>empty purſe,</hi> a <hi>decayed Fortune,</hi> a <hi>distempered Body,</hi> a <hi>guilty accuſing Conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. And all this for a little ſenſuall <hi>mirth</hi> &amp; <hi>pleaſure,</hi> for wine, &amp; women, for a feather, a fancy, an humour, a luſt.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Te miſeriae, te aerumnae premunt omnes, qui te Beatum, qui te florentem putas: Tuae libidines te torquent, tu dies noctesque cruciaris. Te conſcientiae ſtimulant maleficiorum tuorum, te metus exanimant judiciorum, atque legum quocunque aſpexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, ut furiae; ſic tuae tibi occurrunt incuriae, quae te reſpirare non ſinunt — Cicero.</note> Wheras if you would ſeriously return to God, &amp; walk humbly, &amp; circumſpectly before him, you will quickly be able <hi>joyfully</hi> to relate from your own Experience, the <hi>contrary fruit</hi> of holy Obedience. Remember therfore the <hi>vinegar,</hi> and the <hi>Gall</hi> of former ſins, and return <hi>no more</hi> to folly. Eſpecially conſidering that,</p>
            <p>§ 4. <hi>If ſin do thus correct the ſinner in this Life, how much more ſeverly will it do ſo in the next?</hi> If the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſin in this world, are oftentimes ſo dreadfull, how much more intolerable will they be in that which is to come? never did any ſinner without Repentance eſcape the juſtice of God; but ſooner or later his ſin did <hi>find him out.</hi> You cannot ſwallow poyſon, but you
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37239:25"/>will feel the effects of it. Even thoſe ſins you now ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye &amp; glory in, ſhall be your Everlaſting puniſhment. Tho you ſhould not be ſcourged &amp; chaſtened in this world, as many others are. Conſcience that is now aſleep, will ere long awake to purpoſe; &amp; be faithfull to its office when the moſt ſtinging apphrehenſions of your own guilt, ſhall vex &amp; torture your Souls, with a fruitleſs remorſe for paſt folly, &amp; remedileſs despair un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an intolerable wrath.</p>
            <p>All thoſe inquities, which you deſignedly forget, are written down in God's book of Remembrance. And the day is haſtening when a ſtrict Reckoning will be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; &amp; juſtice impartially executed, on thoſe who will not now <hi>believe</hi> a <hi>future Judgment;</hi> &amp; on thoſe who <hi>live,</hi> as if they did not <hi>expect</hi> it.</p>
            <p>It is obſeruable in the word of God, or may be infer'd from thence, to the glory of divine juſtice, that in the proceedings of the laſt day, God will <hi>ſuit</hi> &amp; <hi>proportion</hi> the <hi>future punnishment</hi> of flagitions men, to their <hi>preſent ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every vice ſhall have its proper torment: &amp; the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries which now correct men, as the Beginning of <hi>Hell,</hi> ſhall be then conſummate. Is not the Diſorder &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, the Everlaſting Pain &amp; ſhame of Hell, begun to be inflicted on ſinners in this Life? ſome <hi>impieties</hi> are now <hi>troubleſome</hi> &amp; <hi>painfull,</hi> the full wages will be <hi>exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite</hi> &amp; <hi>intolerable anguiſh.</hi> As there is nothing more <hi>loath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37239:26"/>ſome</hi> then ſome crimes; there ſhall be <hi>ſtench</hi> in the lake of <hi>Brimſtone</hi> here after. Sinners are <hi>now</hi> in <hi>ſlavery</hi> to their luſts, &amp; led <hi>Captive</hi> by the <hi>Devil;</hi> &amp; in the <hi>priſon</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> there are <hi>chains</hi> of Everlaſting <hi>Darkneſs.</hi> They ſhall <hi>reap</hi> as they <hi>ſowed;</hi> &amp; every man <hi>receive according to his works.</hi> God's Eternal <hi>curſe</hi> ſhall be the portion of the Impious <hi>ſwearer,</hi> &amp; <hi>Blaſphemer. Outer Darkneſs</hi> is reſerved for the willfull <hi>deſpiſers</hi> of natural, &amp; Euangelicall <hi>Light.</hi> The <hi>Atheiſts</hi> heart ſhall tremble under the vengeance of that <hi>God</hi> whoſe being &amp; authority he denied. The <hi>Glutton's teeth</hi> ſhall <hi>gnash;</hi> The <hi>Laſcivions</hi> &amp; <hi>unclean</hi> be tormented in unquenchable <hi>flames,</hi> &amp; vainly ſigh for a <hi>drop</hi> of water to <hi>cool</hi> their tongues.</p>
            <p>As they who were <hi>uſefull</hi> in the world, &amp; did <hi>good</hi> to others, ſhall <hi>ſhine as ſtars</hi> in <hi>glory;</hi> the <hi>malicious, ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> &amp; <hi>Envious,</hi> ſhall <hi>gnaw</hi> their own bowells. As the <hi>Lovers of Peace,</hi> ſhall <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of Peace, &amp; be bleſſed; <hi>Furious, Paſſionate, Angry, Turbulent</hi> ſinners ſhall <hi>rave</hi> &amp; <hi>roar</hi> for ever under the wrath of God. As the <hi>mercifull shall find mercy;</hi> the <hi>Covetons,</hi> &amp; <hi>uncharitable</hi> ſhall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their loſt opportunites of doing good, with extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me regret; &amp; the thoughts of their unimployed <hi>Riches</hi> be as <hi>Thorns</hi> in their ſides. As the <hi>meek</hi> &amp; <hi>Humble shall be exalted;</hi> The <hi>proud</hi> ſhall be covered with <hi>Shame:</hi> &amp; <hi>thrown down</hi> to the bottom of <hi>contempt.</hi> As the <hi>Diligent ſoul</hi> ſhall be rewarded with a glorious recompence; the <hi>ſlothfull</hi> ſhall lament their ſtupid <hi>neglicence;</hi> in trifling
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37239:26"/>away their precious <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> without a poſſibility of retrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing them. As holy <hi>Mourners shall</hi> then <hi>be comforted;</hi> the <hi>merry Jovial ſinner,</hi> who now laughs at ſerious piety, &amp; derides Religion as a melancholy humour, shall <hi>weep</hi> &amp; <hi>wail,</hi> for ever. Every impenitent ſinner shall after Death be condemned to a ſtate of unſpeakable miſery: not only far beyond the preſent punishments of ſin; but infinitely above all we can now apprehend or fear; to continue as long as God &amp; Heaven indure. i: e. it shall be without the leaſt hope of an intermiſſion or Period. And <hi>this</hi> without unfeigned Repentance, you will find to your coſt, when 'tis too late, to be no groundleſs <hi>fancy,</hi> or melancholy <hi>Dream,</hi> no <hi>politick device,</hi> or fine contrivance to keep the world in awe; but the <hi>words of ſoberneſs,</hi> &amp; the certaine truth of God. Therfore</p>
            <p>§. 5 <hi>This may abundantly convince us of the great abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity &amp; ſottishneſs of moſt ſinners, in the proſecution of their Luſts.</hi> Who turn the deaf ear to all thes loud reproofs &amp; ſmart corrections of their own Sin. Tho God hath made the wages of Iniquity to be troubleſome &amp; afflictive in this world, as well as threatned eternal ſorrows to the Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hereafter; tho ſome crimes do not only <hi>merit</hi> pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, at the hands of Juſtice, but <hi>inflict</hi> it; yet foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish ſinners court their own miſery, with the refuſal of Happineſs. They will feed upon <hi>husks,</hi> when <hi>Manna</hi> is offer'd them: they forſake the <hi>Fountaine of liveing Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> to purchaſe a <hi>Feaver:</hi> they neglect an Everlaſting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37239:27"/>
               <hi>Heaven,</hi> in the other world, for the Beginnings of <hi>Hell,</hi> in this. They forfeit &amp; relinquish the favor of God, and peace of conſcience, &amp; eternel Life, for the imbraces of an Harlot, for unjuſt gaine, for Drunkenneſs &amp; Riot, &amp; ſuch like follies, with the afflictive conſequences that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them in this Life.</p>
            <p>As if <hi>Paine</hi> were preferable to <hi>eaſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>diſquiet</hi> to <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,</hi> &amp; <hi>contentment:</hi> as if <hi>Trouble</hi> were better than <hi>Peace:</hi> &amp; <hi>Poverty</hi> than <hi>Riches.</hi> As if <hi>ſickneſs</hi> were more deſireable than <hi>health;</hi> &amp; <hi>Disapointment</hi> than <hi>Certainty:</hi> and the <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> &amp; anguish of an <hi>accuſing Conſcience,</hi> then <hi>calmneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity</hi> of <hi>mind.</hi> As if a <hi>long</hi> and <hi>happy Life,</hi> with the Love of God, and the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, and the joyfull proſpect of a future bleſſedneſs after this Life is ended, were leſs eligible than a <hi>miſerable, shamefull,</hi> and <hi>untimely Death.</hi> Is it like <hi>Men,</hi> who have rational Souls, to make ſuch a choice? But t' is more foolish and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, if you are conſidered as <hi>profeſſing Chriſtians;</hi> to betray your <hi>God</hi> for a <hi>luſt;</hi> your <hi>Redeemer,</hi> with all the purchaſe of his death, for <hi>Paine,</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> and loos your immortal <hi>Souls,</hi> redeemed by his precious <hi>Bloud,</hi> not for <hi>nothing</hi> only, but for what is <hi>worſe:</hi> and in order to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable <hi>for ever,</hi> choos to be ſo <hi>for the preſent.</hi> Can you look upon <hi>Sin</hi> with all thes <hi>disadvantages;</hi> and hath it, can it poſſibly have, any <hi>beauty</hi> to intice &amp; charm you? But you will object, it may be, that many who live in Sin, do not meet with thes miſcheivous effects &amp; conſequences,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37239:27"/>upon the account wherof I would diſſuade you from it. Therfore</p>
            <p>§ 6. <hi>We ought to conſider that 'tis very conſiſtent with the Juſtice of God, &amp; reconcileable to his wisdom, that all wicked men should not equally receive the correction &amp; punnishment of Sin in this world.</hi> Many men may ſo far bridle their luſts, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleaſures of Sin with ſo much craft &amp; cunning, as to eſcape many of thoſe rebukes &amp; ſmart corrections, which others meet with. We have Inſtances of ſome who ſpend their days in Pride, &amp; Cruelty, Luſt, &amp; Luxury, &amp; Rebellion againſt God, &amp; yet leave this world without any remarkable ſtroke of his anger &amp; <hi>Juſtice:</hi> to the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; <hi>ſtumbling</hi> of Divers who obſerve it.</p>
            <p>In all Ages this hath been a difficult objection againſt the <hi>Providence of God;</hi> &amp; urged on all occaſions by <hi>Atheiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Sadducees</hi> in favor of their cauſe againſt the Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God. And 'tis more eaſy of the two, to give ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſons of the <hi>perſecutions</hi> &amp; <hi>ſufferings</hi> of <hi>good men,</hi> then to ſolve the <hi>Impunity</hi> &amp; <hi>Proſperity</hi> of the <hi>Wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 Job 7: 8. &amp; ſeqq.</note> But neither can be done with clearneſs &amp; ſatisfaction, without the belief of a <hi>Future Judgment;</hi> &amp; both of thes are argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative in their kind to perſuade that <hi>Belief.
<note place="margin">12 Jer. 1.</note> David</hi> himſelf was puzled for a time with this myſtery of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence: <hi>till he went into the ſanctuary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">73 Pſ. 22.</note> &amp; ſeriously conſidered the <hi>latter end</hi> of Sinners. And then he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims againſt himſelf, &amp; cries out of his folly, <hi>How foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish was I &amp; ignorant: I was as a Beaſt before thee.</hi> For the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37239:28"/>Conſideration of another Life, &amp; a Judgment to come will abundantly ſatisfye us of the reaſons of divine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience &amp; long-ſuffering for the preſent.; Why <hi>Sentence againſt Evill doers is not ſpeedily executed,</hi> or not at all in this world. They are condemned by the holy Law of God, &amp; bound over to his final Judgment; &amp; tho the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be delayed for a while, they cannot eſcape the hand of Juſtice, ſince God is Omnipreſent, Allmighty, &amp; lives for ever. And how short is the time of God's forbearance in this Life, if compared with an endleſs duration of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after the judgment day. We have little reaſon to envy them their preſent <hi>Proſperity,</hi> when we conſider that the day of <hi>Execution</hi> is apointed, &amp; that they are haſtening to it;
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2:3.</note> for <hi>their Judgment doth not linger, &amp; their Damnation ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> The honour of God's Juſtice will then be more publickly vindicated, &amp; more openly manifeſt to all the world, then it could be by the preſent punnishment of all great offenders. It will not be long ere they feel the diſmal effects of that Allmighty ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence they now deride; ſee the <hi>Heaven</hi> they have loſt and ſcorned; &amp; ſuffer thoſe intolerable &amp; remedileſs torments which they will not now believe or conſider. In the mean time they are not all of them altogether unpunisht in this world, but feel the lashes of their own guilty ſelf-condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoughts, by inward horror &amp; anxiety of minde, &amp; continual fears of divine Juſtice: Which all their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperity cannot remedy, any more than muſick
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37239:28"/>can cure the ſtone or Gout, or a Crown of gold give eas to the headach. And thes very <hi>fears</hi> of an after reckoning are a mighty check &amp; reſtraint upon thoſe, who are above the controul of humane laws, &amp; have power to defend &amp; juſtifye their crimes. The world would be fill'd with cruelty &amp; bloud, &amp; mankind be deſtroyed by the Luſts of Tyrants, &amp; great Oppreſſiors, were they not in ſome meaſure reſtrained by the fears of a future Judgment, &amp; punishments in another Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some</hi> ſuch it may be are ſpared, in order to their <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> &amp; <hi>Amendment;</hi> for ſome Perſecutors, &amp; Blaſphemers, &amp; notorious Criminals have been called to <hi>Repentance;</hi> &amp; afterwards have been inſtrumental to glorifie that <hi>God,</hi> whom before they affronted &amp; provok't. Or it may be God forbears them, as the <hi>Executioners</hi> of his wrath upon <hi>others,</hi> as the <hi>ſcourges</hi> of the world, to punnish the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of other men. And when they have done his work, they shall be ſeiz'd by his Juſtice, &amp; their latter end be as exemplary &amp; remarkable, as were their
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jam non ad culmina Rerum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Injuſtè creviſſe queror; tolluntur in altum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ut lapſu graviore ruant.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </note> Impieties. Of this Inſtances may be given in the <hi>Roman Emperors,</hi> &amp; others. For of nineteen or twenty <hi>Emperors,</hi> that paſs'd between <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Phyloſopher, &amp; <hi>Claudius</hi> the ſecond, not one of them eſcap't a violent Death. Moreover, God
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37239:29"/>may deſign to inſtruct us in our duty by his own Example, to teach us by his infinite condeſcention &amp; patience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thoſe who provoke him, how to exerciſe meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; forbearance one toward another. It being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible any injury we receive from our fellow-creatures should ever be heightned to ſuch a guilt, as our ſins againſt God are clothed with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But whatever be the reaſon of <hi>Divine Patience,</hi> it is ſo far from being an argument againſt his <hi>Providence,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Future Judgment,</hi> that it may ſerve to eſtablish both. For <hi>ſome ſinners</hi> are now corrected, and purſu'd by his juſtice, leaſt we should queſtion wither he do at all concern himſelf in the affaires of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, or would ever call men to an acount for what they do: &amp; all great offenders <hi>are not,,</hi> that there may be room for the exercize of Faith: &amp; that we may the better ſee the <hi>need</hi> of a <hi>judgment Day,</hi> &amp; believe the <hi>certainty</hi> of it: &amp; that the threatnings of Everlaſting miſeries may have the more influence &amp; effect upon us; becauſe ſome in great meaſure do eſcape the preſent punnishments of their Impiety. And no wonder if the Providence of God in the diſtribution of temporal good &amp; Evil be now more dark &amp; intricate then formerly; that we can not ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve his displeaſure againſt the wicked by preſent punishment, or his approbation of the Righteous by proſperous Events: becauſe we have now leſs need of ſuch indications of divine favor or wrath: ſince the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary revelation which he hath made of himſelf in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37239:29"/>the holy Scriptures, eſpecially in the new Teſtament, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we have a much clearer light to guide us &amp; a fuller &amp; more manifeſt aſſurance of Eternal Rewards &amp; Punishments. But becauſe ordinarily men are chaſtened, &amp; corrected by their wickedneſs in this world. Therfore</p>
            <p>§. 7. <hi>Let us reſolve to avoid Sin, as ever we would avoid being meſerable in both worlds.</hi> The number is not great of thoſe who abhorr <hi>Evill</hi> by contemplating it meerly in the abſtract; or choos piety by viewing in only in a Metaphyſical dreſſe. <hi>Holineſs,</hi> 't is true, should be lov'd for it ſelf, as the image of God, the moſt Excellent &amp; moſt perfect Being: &amp; <hi>Sin</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for its own intrinſick Malignity, the Deformity, &amp; Evill of its nature. But while we dwell in bodies; preſent ſufferings, &amp; temporall calamities will very much affect us: &amp; as they are the uſuall conſequents of Sin, may be likely to diſſuade us from it. Let us therfore <hi>gather grapes from thes thorns, &amp; figs from thes thiſtles, &amp; turn thes ſtones into Bread,</hi> by learning to be wiſe at a cheaper rate then others. Let the Juſtice of God upon them be mercy to us, for our Inſtruction &amp; War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: that we may not be corrected &amp; reproved by our own folly.</p>
            <p>Becauſe ſome have been impious without feeling all thoſe miſerable effects, or but very few of them; shall we therfore run the hazard? will we ſwallow a cup of poiſon, when we are foretold of the fatal conſequence, becauſe ſome have done ſo unawares &amp; eſcap't with their lives? Becauſe ſome have been in a tempeſt, and not drown'd; would we choos to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture our ſelv's in a ſtorm? will any Wiſeman rush upon the point of a ſword, becauſe it may poſſibly miſs his heart, &amp; not <hi>mortally wound</hi> him? wheras in caſe, if it should <hi>not,</hi> yet the <hi>wound,</hi> will coſt him <hi>dear</hi> by <hi>Repentance;</hi> and the dearer ſtill, the longer he delays the remedy.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37239:30"/>
            <p>Be perſuaded therfore to receive inſtruction, before you taſte the bitter fruit of your own folly: &amp; do not purchaſe <hi>Everlaſting</hi> ſorrows at the price of <hi>Temporal.</hi> Be not ſuch Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to your ſelv's, &amp; to your own intreſt, as to run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of being calamitous &amp; afflicted now, to ſecure therby irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable perdition hereafter. But if Sinners intice thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thou not,
<note place="margin">1 Prov. 10: 15.4. c. 15.5. c. 4.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> walk not in the way with them, refrain thy foot from their path. Avoid it, paſſe not by it, turn from it &amp; paſſe away. For the end will be bitter as wormwood &amp;c. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore avoid the occaſions of Sin, leaſt thou give thine honour unto others; &amp; thy reproach be not wiped away; leaſt ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers be filled with thy wealth; &amp; thou mourn at the laſt, when thy Flesh and thy Body are conſumed, &amp; ſay how have I hated Inſtruction, &amp; my heart deſpiſed Reproof. Conſider the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof,</hi> and avoid the <hi>Correction</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> which now it gives you; that thes ſmaller <hi>drops</hi> may not preface a <hi>shower</hi> of vengence: that your <hi>final ruine</hi> be not the conſequent of your incorrigibleneſs under <hi>preſent chaſtiſement:</hi> that <hi>thes Temporal Punnishments</hi> may not introduce more <hi>terrible, inſupportable,</hi> &amp; <hi>endleſs wrath.</hi> Eſpecially ſince our <hi>mercifull Saviour</hi> hath offered to deliver us from <hi>both:</hi> from the <hi>Temporal Punishments</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> by our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Obedience</hi> to his holy <hi>Goſpel;</hi> &amp; from <hi>Everlaſting Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> by that <hi>Eternal Salvation,</hi> wherof he is the <hi>Author</hi> to All that <hi>obey</hi> him, and to none but them.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Beſides the literal faults &amp; fals pointings, Page 3. line 3. read often. p. 4. l. 4. ſar the r. that. l. 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 20. l. 26. r. riotous. p. 36. laſt line r. with.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37239:30"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
